<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="classintro">

<title>Classes and Objects</title>

<sect2 id="importing"><title> Importing Classes</title> 

<para>
Import statements behave the same as in the <trademark>Java</trademark> programming language.
The syntax is: </para>

<programlisting>
import <emphasis>PackageName</emphasis>.<emphasis>ClassName</emphasis>;</programlisting>

and 

<programlisting>import <emphasis>PackageName</emphasis>.*;
</programlisting>

<para>
If import statements are present, they must appear before 
any other application code. The <trademark>JavaFX</trademark> Script programming language defines its own namespace 
for its built-in library classes (packages <code>javafx.*</code>), but standard Java programming language classes 
can also be imported: 
</para>

<programlisting>
import javafx.application.*;
import java.lang.System;

...

</programlisting>



 </sect2>
 
 
 
<sect2 id="defining"><title> Defining Classes</title> 

<para>
The syntax for specifying a class is the <code>class</code> keyword followed by the class name, optionally the <code>extends</code> keyword, and a comma 
separated list of the names of base classes, an open curly brace, a list of attributes and functions that each end in a semicolon, and a closing curly brace.</para>

<para>The JavaFX Script programming language supports 
multiple inheritance, and therefore, defines some new terminology and rules: </para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>A <emphasis>plain class</emphasis> is any class that directly or indirectly extends a class written in the Java programming language.</listitem>

<listitem>A <emphasis>compound class</emphasis> is any class that is not a plain class.</listitem>

<listitem>By default, classes written in the JavaFX Script programming language are compound classses.</listitem>

<listitem>Classes can extend, at most, one plain class. If it does extend a plain class, it becomes 
a plain class. A class can also extend any number of compound classes, or Java programming language interfaces. </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> A plain class is currently translated into a Java class, while a compound class is translated to a Java class and a Java interface.</para>


<para>It is possible to declare a class to as <code>public</code>, which means that it
can be accessed from any script. Otherwise, the class can only be accessed from the containing script (this 
the default.)</para>

<para>
The JavaFX Script programming language does not support constructors; you must use 
 object literals instead. To mimic the 
behavior of a constructor, define a function that returns a new object,
 and invoke that function.</para>

</sect2> 

 
<sect2 id="object"><title>Defining Objects</title>

<para>As described in the previous chapter, the 
preferred way to instantiate a class is with an <emphasis>object literal</emphasis>.
This form of object allocation uses a declarative syntax consisting of the name of the class followed by a curly brace delimited list of attribute initializers. Each initializer consists of the attribute name followed by a colon, followed by an expression that defines its value. However, it is also possible to use the <code>new</code> keyword when creating an object: 
</para>

<programlisting>
import java.io.File;

var tmpPath = "/home/users/docs/tmp.txt"
var myFile = new File("tmp.txt");
</programlisting>

</sect2> </chapter>



