<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Discusses the what and why of JavaFX Script, and then provides
    examples to give you an overview.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Why JavaFX Script?</title>

      <para>There are thousands of programming languages, why use JavaFX? Two
      reasons: ubiquitous delivery and rapid development of graphical
      applications. JavaFX is built on the Java platform which is available on
      everything from cell phones to supercomputers. JavaFX is designed so
      that the developer can express their desired results succinctly and
      simply. Much can be expressed declaratively, including the interactive
      relationships between components, greatly easing development
      complexity.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>What is JavaFX Script?</title>

      <para>JavaFX Script is a scripting language which means it provides fast
      and easy development with less of the armor provided by conventional
      languages. It is thus tailored to moderately sized interactive graphical
      applications rather than programming in the large. It does, however,
      have one of the most important advantages of compile-time typing. That
      is, before your program even runs, it is checked for incompatible
      relationships between data.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>A Taste of JavaFX Script</title>

      <para>But the best way to get the idea of JavaFX Script is to see some
      examples. Don't worry if some of these don't make sense, the rest of
      this Reference will provide the details.</para>

      <para>JavaFX Script programs are written as one or more
      <emphasis>scripts</emphasis>. A script consists of expressions and
      declarations, typically in a file. The following is an expression and
      thus a valid script:</para>

      <programlisting>4</programlisting>

      <para>But it doesn't do anything. So, we could print it using the
      built-in function 'println':</para>

      <programlisting>println(4)</programlisting>

      <para>Which makes it irresistible to show the Hello World script:</para>

      <programlisting>println("Hello, World")</programlisting>

      <para>This script will print:</para>

      <para><computeroutput>Hello, World</computeroutput></para>

      <para>Which really isn't in the spirit of JavaFX since it isn't
      graphical. Refer to the graphics tutorial for that.</para>

      <para>You can, of course, have more complex expressions:</para>

      <programlisting>println("Circumference is { 2*3.1415*7 } ")</programlisting>

      <para>This script will print:</para>

      <para><computeroutput>Circumference is 43.981</computeroutput></para>

      <para>Note that the expression enclosed in braces is computed at runtime
      and inserted into the string.</para>

      <para>This script would be more interesting if we used variables:</para>

      <programlisting>def PI = 3.14159265; 
var r = 7; 
println("Circumference is { 2 * PI * r } ")</programlisting>

      <para>You could also define a function:</para>

      <programlisting>def PI = 3.14159265; 
var r = 7; 
function circumference(radius) { 2 * PI * radius }
println("Circumference is { circumference(r) } ")</programlisting>

      <para>Note that JavaFX Script uses type inference to figure out the type
      of variables and function. Without type inference, this would be
      written:</para>

      <programlisting>def PI : Number = 3.14159265;  
var r : Number = 7; 
function circumference(radius : Number) : Number {
   2 * PI * radius 
} 
println("Circumference is { circumference(r) }")</programlisting>

      <para>You can define a class to represent a real or abstract entity. In
      this case, a point:</para>

      <programlisting>class Point { 
   var x : Integer; 
   var y : Integer; 
   function show() {
      println("Point {x}, {y}")
   } 
} </programlisting>

      <para>This class defines the x and y coordinates and a function to
      display the Point.</para>

      <para>We can create an instance of the Point and assign it to a variable
      like this:</para>

      <programlisting>var myPoint = Point { 
   x: 12
   y: 9
}</programlisting>

      <para>Note that the x and y instance variables are set during
      creation.</para>

      <para>Finally we can ask the point to print itself by calling the show()
      function defined in the Point class (above).</para>

      <programlisting>myPoint.show()</programlisting>

      <para>This will print:</para>

      <para><computeroutput>Point 12, 9</computeroutput></para>

      <para>For an example-based introduction to JavaFX see the JavaFX Script
      Tutorial.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

